I hope you all are doing very well.
आशा करता हूं आप सब बहुत अच्छे होंगे।
My name is Siddharth Agnihotri.
मेरा नाम है सिद्धार्थ अग्निहोत्री स्टडी
Welcome to Study Gloss.
ग्लोस पे आपका बहुत-बहुत स्वागत है।
Friends, today we will talk about such a
दोस्तों आज हम बात करेंगे
topic, I will give you such an analysis
एक ऐसे टॉपिक की मैं आपको एक ऐसा एनालिसिस
that your mind will open up.  See the
दूंगा कि आपका दिमाग खुल जाएगा। देखिए किस
way geopolitics is happening.  Will
तरीके से जिओपॉलिटिक्स हो रही है। आर्मी
not call on Army Day.  Hey, who
डे में नहीं बुलाएंगे। अबे आर्मी डे में
knows if you might have been invited on Army Day.  The crowd has
बुलाया भी हो क्या पता तुमको। क्राउड है
not come.  Army Day 14 June 14 June America
नहीं आया। आर्मी डे 14 जून 14 जून अमेरिका
's Army Day Asim Munir is coming.  The crowd did
का आर्मी डे आसिम मुनीर आ रहे हैं। क्राउड
not come there, it is possible that they were called there.
ही नहीं आया वहां पर हो सकता है बुलाया
You never know because he had
हो। यू नेवर नो क्योंकि चार दिन से तो ये
lunch in America for the last four days.
अमेरिका में का लंच किया।
So let's talk.  Donald Trump will
तो चलिए बात करते हैं। डॉनल्ड ट्रंप की जो
also talk to Modiji about what he has discussed.
बात हुई है मोदी जी से वो भी बात करेंगे।
But first let's talk about our amazing
लेकिन सबसे पहले बात करेंगे हमारे शानदार
course YouTube Plus Thumbnail.  This is a course on SEO plus
कोर्स YouTube प्लस थंबनेल। ये एसइओ प्लस
thumbnail.  If you
थंबनेल का कोर्स है। अगर आप YouTube चैनल
want to grow your YouTube channel.  today is the last day.  The
को आगे बढ़ाना चाहते हैं। आज आखिरी दिन
course costs just ₹400.  Today this
है। मात्र ₹400 का कोर्स है। आज ये
YouTube coupon code will end.
YouTube जो कूपन कोड है ना दैट विल एंड।
So the link is given in the description comment box.
सो डिस्क्रिप्शन कमेंट बॉक्स में लिंक
So friend, you got a red carpet welcome.
दिया है। तो दोस्त रेड कारपेट वेलकम मिला
Red Carpet You know that the
है। रेड कारपेट आपको पता है कि इनके लिए
red carpet has been laid out for them to come and sit
लाल कारपेट बिछा दी गई है कि आइए बैठिए
because a condition has been placed, what is the condition?  I
क्योंकि एक शर्त रखी है शर्त क्या? मुझे
think the condition is that we will give you the Nobel Peace
तो लगता है शर्त है ये कि आपको नोबेल पीस
Prize.  Donald Trump is the
प्राइज हम दे देंगे। डोनल्ड ट्रंप को वो
crazy man I told you he is.  He is a complete mad
एक मैंने बताया पागल आदमी है। पूरा पागल
man.  Ok?  He is narcissistic,
आदमी है। ठीक है? उसको नार्सिसिस्टिक
he has extreme narcissism.  Ok?
एक्सट्रीम नार्सिसिज्म है उसको। ठीक है?
Now, for those who do not know what Narcissistic
अब जिसको नहीं पता नार्सिसिस्टिक
Personality Disorder is, I have given
पर्सनालिटी डिसऑर्डर क्या होता है मेरे
so many lectures, just type Narcissistic
कितने लेक्चर है आप बस नार्सिसिस्टिक
Personality Disorder, study
पर्सनालिटी डिसऑर्डर डाल दीजिए स्टडी
close and you will get to know, so now what has happened is that
क्लोज आपको पता चल जाएगा तो अब क्या है ना
Pakistan has understood his behaviour just
कि पाकिस्तान ने उसके बिहेवियर को समझ
like India is understanding it and is
लिया है जैसे भारत समझ रहा है और वो सारी
doing all those things that Donald Trump likes.
चीजें कर रहा है जो डॉनल्ड ट्रंप को पसंद
Ok?  So here Donald Trump first
है। ठीक है? तो यहां पे डॉनल्ड ट्रंप पहले
rolls out the red carpet and welcomes him.  And
रेड कारपेट बिछाते हैं वेलकम करते हैं। और
after that he says for Asim Munir, Aha
उसके बाद बोलते हैं आसिम मुनीर के लिए आहा
Fantastic Man I love Pakistan.  Oh my
फैंटास्टिक मैन आई लव पाकिस्तान। ओह माय
God.  Don Trump is singing the song Dil Dil Pakistan.
गॉड। दिल दिल पाकिस्तान गाना गा रहे हैं
And this is the same Donald Trump who was
डॉन्ड ट्रंप। और यही डॉनल्ड ट्रंप जो है
saying in 2018 that Pakistan is a
जो अभी 2018 में कह रहे थे कि पाकिस्तान
liar and a deceiver.
झूठा है, मक्कार है। धोखा देने के अलावा
He doesn't know anything except cheating.
इसको कुछ भी नहीं आता है।
And now he is doing all those
और अब ये वो सारी गतिविधियां कर रहा है
anti-India activities.  Thank me.  Thank me.  I had
एंटी इंडिया। थैंक्स मी। थैंक्स मी। मैंने
told you in my old lectures that if this Don Trump comes, he will
बोला था कि अगर ये डॉन्ड ट्रंप आ गया तो
ruin it.  Mad man, I have been
ये बर्बाद कर देगा। पागल आदमी मैं आज से
saying this for a long time now.  I can
इसको बहुत पहले से कह रहा हूं। मैं
understand what kind of personality the friends have.
पर्सनालिटी समझ लेता हूं दोस्तों किस
Ok?  So I told me
तरीके की है। ठीक है? तो मुझे मैंने बोला
but at that time you guys were abusing me a lot.  Oh
लेकिन तब आप लोग बहुत गरिया रहे थे। अरे
no Sir, when Don Trump comes we
नहीं सर डॉन ट्रंप आएंगे तो अंगना
will decorate the courtyard.  Donald Trump will do it for India.  He
सजाएंगे। डोनल्ड ट्रंप भारत के लिए कर
did nothing for India.
देंगे। एक कुछ नहीं किया भारत के लिए।
All steps are against India, he is such a man.  I
सारे कदम भारत के खिलाफ वो ऐसा ही आदमी
don't get along with his wife.  He
है। उसकी बीवी से नहीं बनती अपनी। उसकी
doesn't get along with anyone, brother.  He is a dangerous man.
किसी से नहीं बनती भाई। खतरनाक आदमी है
Ok?  So Donald Trump has said that
वो। ठीक है? तो डॉनल्ड ट्रंप ने यही बोला
look, I have said again that I have
है कि देखो हमने फिर से बोला कि हमने जो
personally defused a huge war between
है पर्सनली जो है एक बहुत बड़ा वॉर
Pakistan and India.
पाकिस्तान भारत में डिफ्यूज कर दिया। कल
Just yesterday PM Modi scolded
ही पीएम मोदी ने आधे घंटे गरियाया था
Donald Trump for half an hour saying listen son, you have
डॉनल्ड ट्रंप को कि सुनो बेटा तुमने वॉर
not stopped the war, neither will we accept mediation nor have
नहीं रोकी है ना हम मीडिएशन एक्सेप्ट
you ever done it, again after the phone call
करेंगे ना कभी तुमने किया फिर से फोन कॉल
he said that no no I stopped the
के बाद ये बोल दिया कि ना ना आई स्टॉप्ड
war between Pakistan and India,
दी वॉर बिटवीन पाकिस्तान एंड इंडिया आई
this is narcissism, I
यही नार्सिसिज्म होता है आई कि मैंने
stopped the war between Pakistan and India,
पाकिस्तान और भारत के बीच में वॉर रोक दी
contempt that PM Modi told him now no
डिस्पाइट कि पीएम मोदी ने उसको बोला अब
one will look into it, this statement is being
उसको कोई नहीं देखेगा ये वाला जो बयान है
printed everywhere, this is being printed everywhere,
ना यही सब जगह छप रहा है हर जगह यही छप
after that Don Trump is saying that sir
उसके बाद डॉन्ड ट्रंप ये कह रहे हैं कि सर
this is personal diplomacy and
ये तो पर्सनल डिप्लोमेसी है और जो ट्रेड
due to trade pressure, nuclear
का प्रेशर है इसकी वजह से न्यूक्लियर
armed neighbours deescalated.  We
आर्म्ड नेबर्स ने डीएस्केलेट किया। हमने
gave a trade deal to India
ट्रेड डील दी पाकिस्तान भारत को और
because Pakistan was about to launch a big attack.
क्योंकि पाकिस्तान बड़ा हमला करने वाला
This is being said and yesterday Vikram
था। ऐसा बोला जा रहा है और कल विक्रम
Mishra also said the same thing and India said that you will
मिश्री ने भी यही बोला और भारत ने बोला कि
attack.  They have the capability to
हमला करोगे। उनकी औकात है इतनी इतने बम
drop so many bombs that half of their air force i.e. 20% was destroyed.
मारे ना कि उनकी आधी 20% एयरफोर्स खत्म हो
His call came with fear.  Is it okay
गई थी। डर के मारे उनका फोन आया। ठीक है
?  So here I said that both are nuclear
ना? तो यहां बोला कि दोनों ही न्यूक्लियर
countries and I got it stopped again
कंट्रीज हैं और मैंने इसको रुकवा दिया फिर
from Prime Minister Modi ji.  I spoke and
से प्रधानमंत्री मोदी जी से। मैंने बात की
now I also said that I had also talked
अब ये भी बोल दिया कि मैंने बात भी की थी
to PM Modi ji.  Very good, PM Modi has
पीएम मोदी जी से। बहुत ही अच्छा पीएम मोदी
also been praised a lot.  Let us see this also.  It's
की भी बड़ी तारीफ की है। चलिए ये भी देख
not like that.
लेते हैं। ऐसा नहीं है। पीएम मोदी की भी
He also said about PM Modi that Modi is a
उन्होंने भी बोला कि जो मोदी जो है वो
fantastic man.  He is a very nice man.
फैंटास्टिक आदमी है। बहुत ही बढ़िया आदमी
Ok?  And Pakistan is our friend.
है। ठीक है? और पाकिस्तान तो हमारा दोस्त
This is what he is doing bluntly.  And
है। ये दो टूक जो है ये कर रहा है। और
here Michael Kugelman, a defense
यहां पे माइकल कुगलमैन जो कि डिफेंस
analyst, explains something.  He tells
एनालिस्ट है वो कुछ बताते हैं। वो बताते
that look, look, whatever happened yesterday between Trump and
हैं कि देखिए कल जो बात हुई है ट्रंप और
Modi, Modi ji made it clear that he
मोदी की तो मोदी जी ने साफ कर दिया कि
said on his face that you have not
मुंह पे बोल दिया कि आपने कुछ भी नहीं
done anything brother, and you have not done anything.  Isn't it?
किया भैया और कुछ भी नहीं किया है। है ना?
But why is there love for Pakistan?
लेकिन पाकिस्तान का प्यार क्यों है?
Well, Pakistan's love for America is
अमेरिका के लिए तो खैर पाकिस्तान का प्यार
always there. Why is America loving Pakistan so much
हमेशा अमेरिका क्यों इतना पाकिस्तान को
?  I have said many times that Pakistan
प्यार कर रहा है? पाकिस्तान मैंने कई बार
is a country for sale.  You throw money and he is
बोला वो बिकाऊ देश है। आप पैसे फेंके वो
standing there to dance.  So what happened this time
खड़ा है नाचने के लिए। तो इस बार क्या
?  A condition has been placed.  What are the conditions
हुआ? शर्त रखी हुई है। क्या शर्त रखी हुई
?  First of all, the conditions of the Nobel Peace Prize.
है? पहली बात तो नोबेल पीस प्राइज की
Donald Trump wants the Nobel Peace Prize.  It is
शर्त। डोनल्ड ट्रंप को नोबेल पीस प्राइज
needed at any cost.  They have to
चाहिए। किसी भी हाल में चाहिए। उनको वॉर
stop the war.  He also says in Iran and Israel
रुकवाना है। वो ईरान इजराइल में भी कहते
that I want an end.  Rather, one of his
हैं कि मैं अंत चाहता हूं। बल्कि उनके जो
supporters, Mega Maga Bhaiya Tucker Kasan, who used to
सपोर्टर्स हैं मेगा मागा भैया टकर कासन ने
support Donald Trump a lot, has come to Dhar's house.
धर के घर आया है जो कि बहुत ज्यादा सपोर्ट
Ok?  Elon
करते थे डॉनल्ड ट्रंप को। ठीक है? एलॉन
Musk left.  His own
मस्क ने साथ छोड़ दिया। उनके खुद के
supporters are abandoning him.  Now
सपोर्टर्स उनका छोड़ रहे हैं। अब अगले साल
mid-term elections are to be held in America next year in 2026.
2026 में अमेरिका में मिड टर्म इलेक्शन
Donald Trump will lose.
होने हैं। हार जाएंगे डॉनल्ड ट्रंप।
Donald Trump will go on to be stamped as the
डॉनल्ड ट्रंप ये ठप्पा लगवा के जाएंगे कि
worst President in American history.
वर्स्ट प्रेसिडेंट इन अमेरिकन हिस्ट्री।
Worst president.  After this, people will be
वर्स्ट प्रेसिडेंट। इसके बाद लोग जो है
scared that what is happening in Los Angeles
डरेंगे कि भाई लॉस एंजेलिस में जो हो रहा
never happened before.  Ok?  The Marines are
है वो कभी नहीं हुआ। ठीक है? मरींस जो है
fighting in the streets.  Donald Trump will
वो सड़कों पे लड़ रहे हैं। डॉनल्ड ट्रंप
destroy America.
तोड़ देंगे अमेरिका को।
it's gonna happen.  Now here there is a
ये होने वाला है। अब यहां पाकिस्तान के
lot of love for Pakistan, meeting with terrorists
लिए भर-भर के प्यार, आतंकवादियों के साथ
, Syria Alshar on whom a huge bounty was
मीटिंग, सीरिया अलशार जिसके ऊपर इतना इनाम
placed.  So they are telling the world
रखा था। तो दुनिया जो है ये बता रहे हैं
that now look at the world in Washington, this
कि अब देखिए वा द वर्ल्ड इन वाशिंगटन कि
news is spread in all the corridors of America that it needs Pakistan
खबर फैरी हुई है कि पाकिस्तान उसको चाहिए
because pressure has to be created on Iran.
क्यों क्योंकि ईरान के ऊपर प्रेशर बनाना
What does it mean to stop the Iran-Israel war? That basis is
के लिए रुकवाने का मतलब क्या है कि बेसिस
needed in Pakistan also.  As many air
चाहिए पाकिस्तान में भी। जितना हो सके एयर
bases as possible are needed.  And after that Khamenei has to
बेसिस चाहिए। और उसके बाद खामेनी को जितने
persuade all the Ayatollahs to
आयतुल्लाज़ हैं उनको मनाना है कि सुनो
sit at the negotiating table.  But it will
नेगोशिएटिंग टेबल पे बैठो। लेकिन अभी ऐसा
happen now.  You think Iran is preparing for a long war
होगा। आपको लगता है ईरान एक लंबे वॉर के
and Iran-Pakistan
लिए तैयारी कर रहा है और ईरान पाकिस्तान
enmity Pakistan is such a stupid country.
में दुश्मनी पाकिस्तान इतना बेवकूफ देश
He has made such a big mistake.  First
है। उसने इतनी बड़ी गलती कर दी है। पहले
he tells Iran that we will help you.
वो ईरान को कहता है हम तुम्हारी मदद
And as soon as he says that you hit me
करेंगे। और जैसे ही वही है ना कि तू मार
son, I am behind you.  The chance came and he ran away.
बेटा मैं तेरे पीछे हूं। मौका आया भाग
Cheated first of all.  Their admirers
गया। सबसे पहले धोखा दिया। इनके इश्कदार
fearfully say that we are not going to help Iran.
डरते डरते ये बोलते हैं कि हम ईरान की मदद
Forget it, we will help Iran.
नहीं करने वाले। भूल जाओ हम ईरान की मदद
This is accounting.  Asim Munir is having
करेंगे। यह हिसाब किताब है। आसिम मुनीर तो
lunch with Kas from America.  Do you
अमेरिका से कस के साथ बैठ के लंच कर रहे
know what will happen with this?
हैं। इससे पता है क्या होगा? इस्लामिक
Who will the Islamic world ignore?  From Pakistan.
वर्ल्ड कन्नी काटेगा किससे? पाकिस्तान से।
Now, the entire world, the entire Islamic world, there are around
अब पूरी दुनिया पूरा इस्लामिक वर्ल्ड जो
70 countries.
है 70 के करीब वो सब 70 देशों के करीब।
They will realize that this trust is
उनको ये पता चल जाएगा कि यह भरोसे लालायक
not worthy.  But what's the bigger deal?
नहीं है। लेकिन इससे बड़ी बात क्या है?
Donald Trump said, look, today I
डॉनल्ड ट्रंप ने बोला कि देखिए आज मैं
met Asim Munir and I am honoured today.
आसिम मुनीर से मिला एंड आई एम ऑनर्ड टुडे।
Why have I called such a nice man
इतना बढ़िया आदमी मैंने क्यों इसको बुलाया
?  Because I wanted to thank him
है? क्योंकि मैं इसको थैंक यू बोलना चाहता
that he did not go to the war.  What is
था कि यह वॉर में नहीं गए। क्या बात बोल
this brother saying, he was made a Field Marshal, the
रहा है ये भाई फील्ड मार्शल इसको बनाया
defeated Marshal said that he did
गया हारा हुआ मार्शल बोला कि ये वॉर में
not go to the war and here he said that I should
नहीं गया और यहां पे इन्होंने बोला कि मैं
also thank PM Modi.  I
पीएम मोदी को भी थैंक बोलना। थैंक यू
want to say thank you.  Both of them are very
बोलना चाहता हूं। ये दोनों बहुत ही
smart people.  Who said that this
स्मार्ट लोग हैं। जिन्होंने ये कहा कि जो
war should not turn into a nuclear war.
वॉर है उसको न्यूक्लियर वॉर में ना तब्दील
Well, it is Don Trump who is talking about nuclear war also.
होने। अच्छा न्यूक्लियर वॉर भी डॉन्ड
Neither India
ट्रंप ही बोल रहे हैं। ना भारत बोल रहा है
nor Pakistan is saying that we were going to go to a nuclear
ना पाकिस्तान बोल रहा है कि हम न्यूक्लियर
war.  This is what
वॉर में जाने वाले थे। यही बोल रहे हैं
Donald Trump is saying and since then
डॉनल्ड ट्रंप तब से न्यूक्लियर न्यूक्लियर
he has been shouting nuclear rhetoric.
रेटोरिक इन्होंने चिल्ला के रखा हुआ है।
After that he said this when he was
उसके बाद इन्होंने ये बोला कि जब इनको लंच
told during lunch that look, he will
में अब यहां जो ये बोला कि देखिए नोबेल
get the Nobel Peace Prize.  Asim Munir
पीस प्राइज जो है इनको मिलेगा। आसिम मुनीर
proposed to Donald Trump.  That means
ने डॉनल्ड ट्रंप को प्रपोज किया। यानी कि
Pakistan is backing this.
पाकिस्तान इसके लिए बैक कर रहा है।
Well, Pakistan has no status.
पाकिस्तान की खैर कोई औकात नहीं। उसकी कोई
No one will listen to him.  But Donald Trump was happy with this.  Is it
नहीं सुनेगा। लेकिन डॉनल्ड ट्रंप इससे खुश
okay?  Yes brother, let me get the
हो गए। ठीक है ना? कि हां भैया चलो हमको
Nobel Peace Prize.  Now see, Donald Trump is
नोबेल पीस प्राइज। अब देखिए डॉनल्ड ट्रंप
very happy because the
इसलिए भी बहुत ज्यादा खुश है क्योंकि
Kashmir issue is unresolved.  Ok?  And
कश्मीर का मुद्दा अनसॉल्वड है। ठीक है? और
one country, Pakistan, was always ready and is ready
एक देश पाकिस्तान हमेशा से रेडी था रेडी
because it knows that we have
है क्योंकि उसको पता है कि हमने कश्मीर पे
forcefully occupied Kashmir.  And the Indus
जबरदस्ती ऑक्युपाइजेशन की हुई है। और इंडस
Water Treaty is suspended.  India has said
वाटर ट्रीटी सस्पेंडेड है। भारत ने बोला
that it has also told Donald Trump that if
है कि डॉनल्ड ट्रंप को भी बोल दिया कि
Pakistan attacks, this time we will
पाकिस्तान हमला करता है तो हम इस बार
retaliate with double the force.  This war will be
दुगनी जवाब से हमला देंगे। ये वॉर होगा
for us.  So Donald Trump has brought a country
हमारे लिए। तो डॉनल्ड ट्रंप एक देश उनके
with him.  One country has clearly said that the
साथ आ गया है। एक देश ने साफ-साफ बोल दिया
meaning of Nobel Peace Prize is to get the
है नोबेल पीस प्राइस का मतलब क्या कि
Kashmir issue solved.  You
कश्मीर का मुद्दा सॉल्व करवाइए। आप नोबेल
take the Nobel Peace Prize.  This is the condition.  So that means at least
पीस प्राइज ले जाइए। यह शर्त है। तो यानी
one country is with them.  Now see
कि एक देश तो उनके साथ है। अब देखिए ये
what they were trying to do.  Look what Donald Trump is that
क्या करना चाह रहे थे। देखिए डॉनल्ड ट्रंप
PM Modi called him yesterday.
क्या है कि कल पीएम मोदी ने कॉल किया। आधे
PM Modi and Donald Trump talked for half an hour and 35 minutes.
घंटे 35 मिनट इन्होंने बात की पीएम मोदी
Donald Trump
और डॉनल्ड ट्रंप ने। डॉनल्ड ट्रंप ने पीएम
invited PM Modi.  Look at the timing.  Those who are
मोदी को इनवाइट किया। टाइमिंग देखिए। जो
saying that we have rejected it.   Did
कह रहे हैं ना कि हमने रिजेक्ट कर दिया।
n't go.  Brother what was the reason behind that?
गए नहीं। भाई उसके पीछे रीज़न क्या था?
Donald Trump wanted to call PM Modi to America
डॉनल्ड ट्रंप पीएम मोदी को अमेरिका तब
when Asim Munir was also there.
बुलाना चाहते थे जब आसिम मुनीर भी वहीं
And Donald Trump wanted
हैं। और डॉनल्ड ट्रंप चाहते थे कि बीच में
Donald Trump to be in the middle.  Here is Asim Munir, here is
डॉनल्ड ट्रंप हो। इधर आसिम मुनीर, इधर
PM Modi.  They wanted a photo of these three and
पीएम मोदी। इन तीनों की फोटो चाहते थे और
after that Donald Trump boasted,
उसके बाद डॉनल्ड ट्रंप शेखी बगारते कि
look, we stopped the war.  If this had happened
देखो देखो हमने वॉर रुकवा दी। ऐसा होता
in life, Asim Munir would have been taken away from there itself.  Are
जिंदगी में वहीं से उठवा लिए जाते आसिम
you understanding?  India would have got it taken away.
मुनीर। समझ रहे हो? भारत उठवा लेता।
That is why PM Modi has outright rejected
इसीलिए पीएम मोदी ने आउटराइटली रिजेक्ट
that we will not come.  Forget America.  Do you
किया है कि हम नहीं आएंगे। अमेरिका भूल
understand brother?  It is in G7.  He said it
जाओ। समझ रहे हो भाई? G7 में है। बोला कि
is Canada.  Come on.  It is right next to it.  He said,
कनाडा है। आ जाओ। बगल में ही है। बोले
I will not come.  Because this was Donald Trump's
नहीं आएंगे हम। क्योंकि यह डोन्ड ट्रंप की
move.  He would call both of them, get their photographs taken
चाल थी। ये बुलाते दोनों से फोटो खिंचवाता
and then say, look, the Nobel Peace Prize has been won.
और उसके बोलते थे देखो नोबेल पीस प्राइस
Kashmir issue resolved.  Donald Trump
हो गया। कश्मीर मुद्दा सुल। डॉनल्ड ट्रंप
even used to say that he has solved the Kashmir issue.  Are
तो ये तक बोलते थे कि कश्मीर मुद्दा सुलझा
you understanding?  So that is why
दिया मैंने। समझ रहे हो? तो इसीलिए इनको
they were sent an invitation to the G7 summit being held here.
G7 यहां पे जो समिट हो रही है इनको
And now there
इनविटेशन भेजा। और वही अब स्पेकुलेशन तो
were speculations that they wanted to do something diplomatic,
थे कि एक डिप्लोमेटिक कु कराना चाहते हैं
but that did not happen.  Out Rightly Well Asim
बट ऐसा हुआ नहीं। आउट राइटली अच्छा आसिम
Munir knows this.  Friends, Asim Munir
मुनीर को ये बात पता है। आसिम मुनीर को
knows this.  Pakistan's
दोस्तों ये बात पता है। पाकिस्तान की
leadership wants India to come to the table
लीडरशिप चाहती है भाई भारत आ जाए टेबल पे
but it also wants us to continue
लेकिन वो ये भी चाहती है कि हम आतंकवाद भी
spreading terrorism.  Which she has always been doing.
फैलाते रहे। जो हमेशा से करती आई है वो।
Brother, in 2021 Bajwa Qamar Javed Bajwa
भैया 2021 में बाजवा कमर जावेद बाजवा पीएम
wanted to invite PM Modi to Pakistan.  You
मोदी को बुलाना चाहते थे पाकिस्तान। आपको
know Imran Khan did not agree.  Imran Khan
पता है इमरान खान नहीं माने। इमरान खान ने
refused.
मना कर दिया।
And today Imran Khan is in jail and Asim Munir is
और इमरान खान आज जेल में है और आसिम मुनीर
out.  And Asim Munir, who is there for the lunch, has
बाहर है। और आसिम मुनीर जो हैं लंच जो
organised such a grand welcome for him,
इतना बड़ा किया है ऐसा भव्य स्वागत
friends, someone like Pervez Musharraf had gone for lunch
दोस्तों किसी परवेज मुशर्रफ गए थे लंच के
in 2001.  And why did he go?  Because that
लिए 2001 में। और वो क्यों गए थे? क्योंकि
war and terror
वो जो वॉर एंड टेरर था जॉर्ज डब्ल्यूh का
needed the support of George W. Bush and Pervez Musharraf.  Is it okay
सपोर्ट चाहिए था परवेज मुशर्रफ का। ठीक है
?  Because brother, where did we get terrorism from Pakistan,
ना? क्योंकि पाकिस्तान से आतंकवाद कहां
Osama bin Laden?
मिला भैया ओसामा बिन लादेन?
Before this Ziaul Haq or any other leader like
इससे पहले जियाउल हक या जितने भी लीडर्स
Ayub Khan have only talked and held
हैं अय्यूब खान उन्होंने खाली बात की है
meetings but such a grand welcome has not been given.
मीटिंग्स की है बट ऐसा भव्य स्वागत नहीं
Why has this happened now?  Because Asim
हुआ है। अब यह क्यों हुआ है? क्योंकि आसिम
Munir himself knew that PM Modi would come
मुनीर खुद पता था उसको कि पीएम मोदी आएंगे
and Asim Munir wanted PM Modi to come.
और आसिम मुनीर चाहता था कि पीएम मोदी आए।
This matter should end and everyone should know that
यह बात खत्म हो और सबको यह पता चले कि
India and Pakistan are good friends, but PM
भारत पाकिस्तान अच्छे दोस्त है लेकिन पीएम
Modi clearly said that we are not coming.
मोदी ने साफ-साफ बोल दिया कि हम नहीं आने
Because what was happening was that
वाले। क्योंकि बात यह हो रही थी ना कि
he was also invited to the military parade.  And
मिलिट्री परेड में भी इनको बुलाया गया। और
who knows, Asim Munir might be there?  You never know.
क्या पता आसिम मुनीर हो वहां पे? यू नेवर
This can definitely happen.  Because the
नो। बिल्कुल हो सकते हैं यह। क्योंकि
crowd that was supposed to come, did not come.
क्राउड ही नहीं आया ना जो आना था।
So here we will meet the Pentagon and
तो यहां पे अभी पेंटागन से मिलेंगे और
also the State Department.  Now
स्टेट डिपार्टमेंट से भी मिलेंगे। अब
tell me, this is a high profile visit
बताइए हाई प्रोफाइल विजिट है ये आसिम
of Asim Munir.  Is it okay?  Now understand one thing that
मुनीर की। ठीक है ना? अब एक चीज समझिए कि
whatever America is doing, the relations between India and
ये जो कर रहा है अमेरिका इससे इंडिया और
America are getting worse.
अमेरिका के रिलेशंस बहुत खराब हो रहे हैं।
And India-America relations cannot deteriorate
और इंडिया अमेरिका के रिलेशन खराब नहीं हो
because India
सकते क्योंकि इंडिया अमेरिका को
gives intellectual power to America.  Ok?  We
इंटेलेक्चुअल पावर देता है। ठीक है? हम
are the GC.  Global Capability Center.  So if
जीसी हैं। ग्लोबल कैपेबिलिटी सेंटर। तो
India
भारत यहां पे अमेरिका के अमेरिका की
grows here in increasing the GDP of America, then America will
जीडीपी को आगे बढ़ाने में बढ़ेगा भारत तो
grow.  There is some slogan like this.  Ok?
बढ़ेगा अमेरिका। ऐसा नारा है कुछ। ठीक है?
And the Indians are all over America,
और इंडियंस जो है ना वो पूरे अमेरिका
Indians are there.  Friends, it would not be wrong to say this.
इंडियंस आर जस। ये बात कहना गलत नहीं होगा
Give us control of America.
दोस्तों। दे कंट्रोल अमेरिका। अफ्रीका को
Who controls Africa?  Indians.
कौन कंट्रोल करता है? इंडियंस। सारे
India has all the business.  There are Indians in West Asia
बिजनेस इंडिया के पास है। वेस्ट एशिया में
too.  There are Indians in West Asia.
भी इंडियंस हैं। वेस्ट एशिया में इंडियंस
10 million people live in the Gulf region.
हैं। 1 करोड़ लोग गल्फ रीजन में रहते हैं।
One pet reaction, look at how many there are in Saudi Arabia and UAE
एक पेट रिएक्ट सऊदी अरब यूएई में देख
and like these
लीजिए कितने सारे हैं और यह जैसे
Pakistanis are laborers or they do lowly jobs,
पाकिस्तानी वो लेबर हैं या वो निचला काम
Indians reach high positions.
करेंगे इंडियंस हाई पोजीशन पे पहुंचते
Reaches a very high position.  Are
हैं। बहुत हाई पोजीशन पे पहुंचते हैं। समझ
you understanding?  So, in a way,
रहे हो? तो एक तरीके से इंडिया अमेरिका का
if the relations between India and America get spoilt, then that is why Americans are
अगर रिलेशन खराब होगा और इसीलिए अमेरिकन
jealous of Indians.  Ok?  What you
जलते भी हैं इंडियन से। ठीक है? जो आप
see is the racism online
देखते हो ना रेसिज्म ऑनलाइन इंडियंस के
against Indians because it moves very fast.
खिलाफ वो इसीलिए है क्योंकि जो बहुत तेजी
Look what Pakistan has to face
से आगे बढ़ता है। देखो पाकिस्तान को क्या
?  They know that people will not move forward.
है? उनको पता है कि लोग आगे नहीं बढ़ेंगे।
Leave them alone.  Ok?  But whoever
छोड़ो इनको। ठीक है? लेकिन जो इंसान आपके
comes in competition with you, you will do that to him.  So
टक्कर में आएगा आप उससे डोगे। तो यहां पे
what is here is that the relations between India and America
क्या है ना कि जो ये इंडिया और अमेरिका के
can get very bad and are getting worse.
रिलेशन बहुत खराब हो सकते हैं और खराब हो
This same Google man said that
रहे हैं। यही Google मैन ने बोला कि ये जो
you are engaging with the Army Chief of Pakistan.
पाकिस्तान के आर्मी चीफ के साथ आप इंगेज
And you hosted us here at the White House.
कर रहे हो। और यहां पे वाइट हाउस में आपने
Ayub Khan Ziaul Haq also held
होस्ट किया। अयूब खान जियाउल हक ने भी
meetings.  But if it is not hosted
मीटिंग्स की। लेकिन होस्ट नहीं किया तो
then the relations between India and America will
इससे इंडिया और अमेरिका के रिलेशन बहुत
deteriorate significantly.  Is it okay?  And the
ज्यादा खराब हो जाएंगे। ठीक है ना? और
most dangerous thing is
सबसे डेंजरस चीज ये है कि पाकिस्तान के
what has Trump said about Pakistan?
बारे में क्या बोला है ट्रंप ने? कितनी
Donald Trump has said so many wrong things about
गलत बातें जितना डॉनल्ड ट्रंप ने
Pakistan and has stopped so many ads.
पाकिस्तान को गरियाया है ना और इतनी एड
But now see, everything has changed.
रोक दी है। लेकिन अब देखिए सब कुछ बदल गया
Now at this time they are calling top generals and
है। अब इस समय टॉप जनरल्स को बुला के
doing press conference.  In South Asia, they
प्रेस कर रहे हैं। साउथ एशिया में ये
show that brother, we are power brokers
दिखाते हैं कि भैया हम तो पावर ब्रोकर हैं
and we should get the Nobel Peace Prize.
और हमने हम मुझे ही नोबेल पीस प्राइज
So these things are why New Delhi will
तो ये चीजें तो इसीलिए न्यू दिल्ली इसको
not tolerate this because the line has been crossed.
बर्दाश्त नहीं करेगा क्योंकि लाइन क्रॉस
We will not tolerate everything
हो चुकी है। हर एक चीज हम नहीं बर्दाश्त
and you need India.  America
करेंगे और आपको भारत की जरूरत है। अमेरिका
needs India.
को भारत की जरूरत है। अमेरिका के साथ
We have a trade deficit with America and
ट्रेड डेफिसिट है हमारा और पीएम मोदी को
now every leader including PM Modi will have to take a very strict
अब तो हर एक लीडर को एक बहुत ही सख्त
stand.  And at the same time
स्टैंड लेना पड़ेगा। और साथ ही साथ यहां
it was also said here that there are
ये भी बोला था कि ये जो मिलिट्री और ईरान
three men regarding the military, Iran and counter terrorism.
और काउंटर टेररिज्म को लेकर तीन मेन है।
One is counter terrorism, one is Iran related
एक तो काउंटर टेररिज्म एक ईरान वाला हिसाब
accounting and the other is their crypto related one.  So
किताब और एक इनका क्रिप्टो वाला। तो
Donald Trump will talk on these three issues – counter
डॉनल्ड ट्रंप जो हैं इन तीन इशू पे काउंटर
terrorism, China, crypto currency and
टेररिज्म, चाइना, क्रिप्टो करेंसी और
critical minerals.  Is it okay
क्रिटिकल मिनरल्स इन पे बात करेंगे। ठीक
?  So now see, crypto currency will
है ना? तो अब देखिए क्रिप्टो करेंसी जो है
destroy Pakistan.  If crypto
वो पाकिस्तान को ले डूबेगा। अगर क्रिप्टो
mining starts.  Is it okay?
माइनिंग शुरू होती है। ठीक है ना? उसके
After that, if we talk about China, Pakistan also
बाद चाइना की बात करें तो पाकिस्तान भी
wants that
चाह रहा है कि चाइना और अमेरिका दोनों के
we should balance our relations with both China and America.
साथ ही हम रिलेशन जो है वो बैलेंस कर लें।
Ok?  Is ISK okay when it comes to counter terrorism
ठीक है? काउंटर टेररिज्म की बात करें तो
?  For example, America just said that we
आईएसके ठीक है? जैसे अभी अमेरिका ने कहा
felt good when you gave them the terrorists of Islamic State Khorasan who have
अच्छा लगा जो कि बॉर्डर पे अफगानिस्तान और
set up bases on the borders of Afghanistan and Iran.   They have
ईरान के बॉर्डर पे बेस बनाए हुए हैं।
established bases on the Afghanistan-Pakistan border.  So they consider Pakistan as an
बनाए हुए हैं। तो पाकिस्तान को ये एक
interlocutor.  That their
इंटरलोक्युटर मानते हैं। कि इनका
influence is more there.  All the
इन्फ्लुएंस वहां पे ज्यादा है। सारे
terrorists listen to him.  And
आतंकवादी इनकी बात मानते हैं। और
Pakistan feels that
पाकिस्तान को लगता है कि इंडस वाटर ट्रीटी
America will be able to put pressure on India on many things including the Indus Water Treaty.
से लेकर बहुत सारी चीजों पर अमेरिका भारत
But India will not listen to the bell.
पर प्रेशर बना पाएगा। पर घंटा नहीं सुनेगा
Keep saying whatever you want to say.  And
इंडिया। जो बोलना है बोलते रहो। और
now Pakistan is saying that it is
पाकिस्तान अब जो है वो वही बता रहा है कि
giving information about the
एक तरीके से इंफॉर्मेशन दे रहा है
terrorists to America, that means it is
आतंकियों की को अमेरिका की अमेरिका आ मतलब
giving information about these terrorists to America
इंफॉर्मेशन दे रहा है इन आतंकी अमेरिका को
and America is
आतंकियों की और अमेरिका जो है इसको बहुत
also praising it a lot because
प्रज़ भी कर रहा है क्योंकि जो स्ट्राइक्स
Pakistan has a hand in the strikes that have taken place.  So
हुई है उसमें पाकिस्तान का हाथ है। तो जिस
see how Pakistan is playing a double game.
देखिए पाकिस्तान कैसे डबल गेम खेल रहा है।
He is supporting these terrorists
वो इन्हीं आतंकियों को सपोर्ट कर रहा है
and is giving this information to America
और यही इंफॉर्मेशन वो अमेरिका को दे रहा
and the same America is striking them.  Is it
है और वही अमेरिका इनके ऊपर स्ट्राइक कर
okay?  So this is it.
रहा है। ठीक है ना? तो यही चीज है।
Rest, you know about Kurila's statement,
बाकी जो कुरिला की स्टेटमेंट है आपको पता
how much
ही है कि उन्होंने कितना ज्यादा
press he has given to Pakistan, he said that
प्रेस किया है पाकिस्तान को बोला कि
Pakistan is very important.  There
पाकिस्तान बहुत ज्यादा जरूरी है। बाइनरी
is no binary switch.  It is important that we
स्विच नहीं है। जरूरी कि हम दोनों देशों
work with both countries.  Now
के साथ काम करें। ये सारी चीजें अब
you know about all these things, Pakistan has said that
पाकिस्तान आपको पता है कि उसने ये बोला है
look, a National Crypto Currency Reserve should be
कि देखो एक नेशनल क्रिप्टो करेंसी रिजर्व
created.  Now let me tell you ideally.
बना। अब आपको मैं आइडली बताता हूं।
Crypto trading is illegal in Pakistan.
पाकिस्तान में क्रिप्टो ट्रेडिंग इललीगल
could you believe?
है। क्या आप विश्वास करेंगे? पाकिस्तान
Crypto trading is illegal in Pakistan and their
में क्रिप्टो ट्रेडिंग इललीगल है और उनके
PM says that we will create a
पीएम बोलते हैं कि हम तो बनाएंगे एक
crypto currency reserve.  You can see
क्रिप्टो करेंसी रिजर्व। आप देख सकते हैं
what kind of country this is.  Where
देश कैसा है ये। जहां पे क्रिप्टो करेंसी
they have declared crypto currency illegal.  He
उन्होंने इललीगल घोषित की हुई है। वो
says that we will create a crypto currency reserve.
बोलते हैं कि हम क्रिप्टो करेंसी रिजर्व
And Donald Trump's family has
बनाएंगे। और डॉनल्ड ट्रंप की ही जो परिवार
invested the most money in crypto.  Are you understanding?  So you can assume this
लगाए हुए हैं। समझ रहे हो? तो आप ये मान
and if we talk about critical minerals as well,
के चलिए और क्रिटिकल मिनरल्स की भी बात है
then there are many such deposits
तो जैसे बहुत सारे इस तरीके के डिपॉजिट्स
in Balochistan.  Isn't it?  Critical
बलचिस्तान में है। है ना? क्रिटिकल
minerals, China has also banned critical minerals.
मिनरल्स जो कि चाइना ने क्रिटिकल मिनरल्स
It has imposed a ban on rare earth elements.
पे उसने रोक लगा दी है। ये सारी चीजें जो
America is finding all these things very
है वो अमेरिका को लग तो रहा है बहुत
good.  But what is happening with this?  Because of this, one
बढ़िया। बट इससे हो क्या रहा है? इससे एक
Pakistani will also be ruined.
तो पाकिस्तानी भी बर्बाद हो जाएगा। पूरी
Completely based on the conditions of America.
तरीके से अमेरिका की जो कंडीशंस है। उसके
After that India will go away and ultimately
बाद इंडिया दूर चला जाएगा और अल्टीमेटली
friends, they will not get anything.
दोस्तों इनको कुछ भी नहीं मिलने वाला।
it is.  What do you think, please
यह है। आपको क्या लगता है मुझे कमेंट
tell me in the comment box.  Rest you can read our course.
बॉक्स में बताइएगा। बाकी आप हमारे कोर्स
YouTube Thumbnail Plus SEO This
को अेल करें। YouTube थंबनेल प्लस एसइओ ये
Amazing Course Use YouTube Coupon Code.
शानदार कोर्स YouTube कूपन कोड यूज़ करें।
Be happy, keep reading.  This is Siddharth
खुश रहिए, पढ़ते रहिए। दिस इज सिद्धार्थ
Agnihotri signing off.
अग्निहोत्री साइनिंग ऑफ।